I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
You may have heard
about a study
suggesting that an enzyme in bananas
that turns bananas brown
can partially destroy a class of nutrients
found in foods like berries.
So, should you stop putting
bananas in your smoothies?
Here are some answers.
We all know there are recommended daily intakes
of essential nutrients like vitamins to prevent
deficiencies, but recently, the first dietary
recommendation for a bioactive food compound
was published. Bioactive food compounds are not
necessary for basic human needs but may have
health benefits. For example, plant metabolites
known as flavonoids. Flavonoids are a type of
polyphenol, of which the most commonly consumed
one is flavan-3-ols, also known as just flavanol.
A review of the literature suggests that 400 to
600 milligrams a day of these flavanols would be
beneficial for cardiovascular protection, such
as the potential for improving blood pressure,
cholesterol, blood sugars, etc. Note that
this is specifically a food guideline,
not a supplement guideline, though really, it's
actually more like a beverage guideline since,
if you look at the primary sources, it's really
tea, green or black, that is the easiest way to
reach those levels. Though there are certainly
some in a variety of berries and cocoa. However,
there's an enzyme called polyphenol oxidase
that can break down these wonderful polyphenols
like flavonoids. That is what makes certain
fruits and vegetables brown when you cut them,
such as bananas and potatoes. Now, why would
a plant do that to itself? Well, apparently,
it is a defense mechanism, part of the plant's
immune system, and when exposed to oxygen, what
happens is that polyphenol oxidase can oxidize
polyphenols into these breakdown products, which
have antimicrobial activity. So when a banana gets
bruised, for example, or you cut open an avocado,
the polyphenol oxidase can start oxidizing
polyphenols into these defensive compounds that
can glom together, forming a dark compound called
melanin, the same class of compounds that darkens
the skin of a banana also darkens our skin too.
Okay, so no problem, we can just not eat bananas
that have turned brown, right? Because that's
visual evidence that many of the polyphenols
have been lost. Ah, but what if you mix that
banana, which is filled with that polyphenol
oxidase enzyme, in a smoothie with polyphenol-rich
foods like berries or cocoa? And why you end up
with less nutrition. Well, big chocolate-funded
researchers sought to find out, and so what they
did: They put about a half cup of cocoa's worth of
cocoa flavanol into a banana-containing smoothie
compared to the same amount in a berry smoothie
with no banana, compared to the same amount of
cocoa blended into a banana smoothie. Right,
so the same amount of those cocoa goodies, but
it's almost as if there was no cocoa in there at
all, presumably because the banana enzymes chopped
up all the chocolate goodies. Let's not presume,
though. They blended up that chocy banana smoothie
again, which was just banana, almond milk, cocoa
flavanol, and then they just measured the level
of flavanols as the smoothie sat for an hour,
and the cocoa flavanols plummeted more than 90%,
a half-life of about 10 minutes. So every
10 minutes, the levels of polyphenols drop
in half. Now, how do we know it was for sure the
polyphenol oxidase enzyme? Because then, if you
add various polyphenol inhibitors, then they block
the effect. Okay, so no problem if you add bananas
to your smoothies, just you have to chug them down
before the enzyme does its job, right? I mean,
presumably, the enzyme would be deactivated
when it hit the acid bath of our stomach,
but you don't know until you put it to the test,
and I love that the researchers did all this. What
they did is this time they had study participants
alternate sips between a straight banana almond
milk smoothie and like chocolate milk, chocolate
flavonoids plus the almond note, right? So there
was no premixing in the blender between the
banana enzyme and the flavanol, just mixing
in the stomach, such an elegant research move.
Okay, so you get 37% less in your bloodstream,
showing that the banana enzyme can still do some
polyphenol damage in your stomach. And indeed,
in simulated stomach acid conditions, yes, the
polyphenol oxidase is indeed down but not out.
Okay, so yeah, if you drink some smoothie with a
banana, it's better not to let it sit around, but
even if you drink it immediately, you can get less
polyphenols in your system than if you had skipped
the banana. But bananas make smoothies so rich
and creamy. I mean, anything we can add to the
smoothie to counter the banana enzyme's effect?
There's one food that has even more polyphenol
oxidase activity than banana, and it's a vegetable
that's not a potato. What vegetable turns brown
that's not a white potato? Oh, white mushrooms.
White button mushrooms have more polyphenol
oxidase activity than even bananas. Now, for
those of you thinking, don't worry, I don't
think I'm expected to be adding any mushrooms to
my smoothies anytime soon. Now, some people do add
avocados to smoothies or make like a chocolate
avocado pudding, and here's the question:
What if you eat mushrooms with a meal packed with
polyphenol-rich foods? Right, might it mix in
your stomach and decrease the absorption, like the
anthocyanin in red cabbage or berries for dessert?
Right, and look, you could also be having some
potatoes with your meal, or eggplant with your
meal. Now note, though, however, this is for fresh
produce, right? So, you know, we're not worrying
about the eggplant, potatoes, and the enzyme is
utterly destroyed by cooking. And look, remember,
we should be cooking our mushrooms anyway, right,
because of the agitoxin. Most of our mushrooms,
you don't have to cook oyster mushrooms, but
the white and crimini and portobello mushrooms,
right? So, problem solved, right? You don't have
to worry about cooked potatoes, cooked eggplant,
cooked mushrooms. Okay, but who wants to cook
their bananas, though? Right, what else could
we put in a smoothie instead? My personal favorite
is mango, which you can buy frozen when it's not
in season. Do we have to worry about that
having a polyphenol-eating enzyme? Well,
what happens when you cut open a mango? Does
it go brown? No, it doesn't go brown. Mango
has maybe 500 times less than that banana. Now,
the apple certainly doesn't surprise me, right,
because what happens with apples, turns brown. But
boy, the smoothie study raises so many interesting
questions, right? So, what, forget smoothies,
should you not add bananas to your oatmeal,
right? Because the bananas in your stomach would
mix with like the berries or the cocoa that you
put in your oatmeal. And indeed, that is what
we should expect. So, I no longer add bananas
to my cran-chocolate pomegranate breakfast bowl.
That was one of my cooking videos, if you missed
it. And since, you know, I don't want to lose any
of those polyphenols, there are so many wonderful
ingredients in that. I don't want to lose any,
don't want any of those destroyed, that 37%
decrease in your stomach when it all mixes with
that enzyme. Okay, but what if you're not making
something chocolatey? This study only tested the
effects of the enzyme on cocoa flavanol, like
they didn't check to see if mixing bananas with
berries would affect the berry phytonutrients,
but the presumption is that it would. And so,
hm, what does that mean for like ready-to-drink
bottled smoothie drinkers that you might find
in the store, right, that may be sitting on
the shelf? Well, if it's been pasteurized,
then it should be okay, right? Because the
heat destroys that enzyme. That's why vegetables
are blanched, you know, before they're frozen,
to destroy the enzymes. Even just heating bananas
to like 70 degrees C, which is like hot tea,
70° C for 2 minutes in the presence of vitamin
C and citric acid, which might come from lemon
juice, for example, would suppress the enzyme by
80%. I'm not suggesting drinking hot smoothies,
but rather that those pasteurized smoothie drinks,
depending on the ingredients, may not have the
same problem as fresh-made smoothies. What about
just adding the vitamin C and citric acid alone,
like putting lemon juice in your smoothie? It only
cuts the enzyme activity by about 133% without the
heating step. However, it does work wonders for
apples. Cut apple, you just add some lemon juice,
and you can cut that activity nearly in half,
explaining why adding lemon juice to your fruit
salad, you know, keeps the apples in your fruit
salad from turning brown. Okay, anything we can
add to a banana smoothie to inhibit the enzyme
so we can still use bananas but somehow block
the enzyme? Well, they used to put sulfites in
fresh fruits and vegetables to block that enzyme
until they were banned in 1986, following cases
of sulfite-induced asthma. They are still used
in dried fruit, though, to prevent browning.
What, so, okay, sulfites are kind of off the
table. But what about what can we do for natural
anti-browning agents to block this puppy? Well,
onion extracts can prevent the browning of
pears, but there has got to be something
better for your smoothies. And indeed, pineapple
juice does seem to help keep apples from browning,
and bananas too, for that matter. But that was
after soaking in pineapple juice for three days,
so it's not clear if it would work right away.
There was a study comparing lemon juice and
white wine to prevent browning in pastry dough.
You've heard of hard cider, hard seltzer, well,
the lemon juice appears to beat out the wine.
So, better a lemon squeeze than drinking a
hard smoothie. That's the story on bananas and
smoothies. So should you not eat bananas? No,
you can eat bananas any time, you just don't want
to eat bananas. You just don't want to have the
bananas in your stomach at the same time you have
other healthy foods like berries, cocoa, and tea.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.